اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Musa(موسى) was very shy and that is, how the mu'min(مؤمن); the believer should be.
He was always covering up his body.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) said; Musa(موسى) is not showing us his body because, he's suffering from some kind of disease.
And they accused him of leprosy, and they accused him of; they said that, syphilis; the expansion of the testicles.
They said; That's why, he's always covering himself up.
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); they used to bath together.
They would go out in a river or in a pool, and they would all take their clothes, and they would just go in, and bath in front of each other.
Musa(موسى) would go alone, and would bath alone, and would not let anyone see him.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wanted Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) to see that, this is not true.
So, Musa(موسى) went to bath.
So, he put his clothes on a rock; on a stone.
And then when he look back; he didn't find the stone, the stone was running away with his clothes.
So, Musa(موسى) is running after the stone, and this in Bukhari(بخاريْ); we'll read the Hadith.
So Musa(موسى) is running after the stone, and he's saying;
ثوبي يا حجر، ثوبي يا حجر
Bring me my clothes back, stone! Bring me my clothes back!
And he's running after the stone.
And the stone took him around Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) so, they could take a look at Musa(موسى); without any clothes.
فَرَأَوْهُ أَحْسَنَ ما خَلَقَ اللَّهُ
They saw the best creation of Allah.
And then, when the issue was done, the stone stopped, by the order of Allah.
So Musa(موسى) had a stick which he would carry with him always, and he started beating the rock; beating the stone.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; And he left on it marks, that could be seen.
He hit it so hard that it left behind marks.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; Oh you, who Believe! Be not; like those who annoyed Musa(موسى),
but Allah cleared him of that which they alleged, and he was honorable before Allah.
Syedina Musaعليه السلام was with the children of Israel(اسرائيل) in the wilderness.
They got lost in the desert.
And Syedina Musaعليه السلام had to spend his life and his efforts dealing with his people.
And Musa(موسى) wanted good for them.
Nevertheless, they were causing him difficulties, and they were being stubborn and difficult to deal with.
So Musaعليه السلام told his people;
وَإِذْ قَالَ مُوسَىٰ لِقَوْمِهِۦ يَٰقَوْمِ لِمَ تُؤْذُونَنِى وَقَد تَّعْلَمُونَ أَنِّى رَسُولُ ٱللَّهِ إِلَيْكُمْ ۖ
Oh my people! Why do you harm me?
When you know that, I am a messenger sent by Allah to you;
why do you harm me?
But Musa(موسى) had to endure all of this difficulty with his people.
And then, his brother; Haroon عليه السلام; the prophet of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; the right hand of Musa(موسى); his advisor; wazeer(وزير); his supporter; his helper throughout this period;
His brother Haroon عليه السلام passed away.
Now, Musaعليه السلام is alone to deal with his nation.
With this huge nation of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); Musa(موسى) was alone.
He lost his close associates, and brother, and advisor; Haroon عليه السلام.
And then Musa(موسى) received a visit from the Angel of Death in the form of a man,
and this Hadith(حديث) is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
The Angel of Death presented himself to Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى); in the form of a human being; a man.
And he came, and he told Musaعليه السلام; Are you ready to die?
Because we know that, the Angel of Death takes our lives without announcement.
But he does not take the life of a Nabi(نَبِي) until, they take permission, and they let them know.
The Angel of Death told Musa(موسى); Are you ready to die?
Musaعليه السلام slapped the angel of death in his face, and he knocked his eye out.
He slapped him in his face, and he knocked his eye out.
So, the Angel of Death went to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and said;
يا ربِّ أرسَلْتَني إلى عبدٍ لا يُريدُ الموتَ
Oh Allah! You have sent me to a man who doesn't wanna die.
And then the Angel of Death says in another Hadith(حديث); this is not in Bukhari(بخاريْ), I think this Hadith(حديث) was narrated by Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ).
He says;
ولولا كرامتُه عليك لشققتُ عليه
And if it is not because, I know that Musa(موسى) is love to you, I would have made his death difficult.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told the Angel of Death; Go back to Musa(موسی)
and tell him to put his hand on the back of an ox
and tell him that, every hair that is under his hand; I will give him one year in his life; for every hair under his hand.
The Angel of Death went to Musa(موسى) and said; Oh Musa(موسى)! Allah is telling you put your hand on the back of an ox,
and Allah will give you for every hair under your hand; one year to live.
Musa(موسى) by now had chance to think about it.
So, he asked the Angel of Death and then what, and then What will happen?
Then the Angel of Death said; Then you will die.
Musa(موسى) said;
فالآنَ اَذِن
Then let me die now.
If in the end; I'm gonna die; let me die now.
We don't know exactly, why Musa(موسى) rejected the angel of death in the beginning?
But Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) says;
Maybe it was because Musa(موسى) had a desire in his heart that wasn't fulfilled yet.
And Musa(موسى) wanted that desire; wanted that hope and aspiration to be fulfilled.
And that desire, is a desire that Musa(موسى) has been living for, and awaiting for a long time in his life.
And that is the promise of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to enter into the Holy Land; Jerusalem.
So Musa(موسى) wanted to have the honour of leading his people into the Holy Land and establishing the Islamic nation.
He wanted to have the honour of leading his people into Jerusalem.
But this was the will of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and when Musa(موسى) realized that it wasn't ordained for him.
He said; Then, let me die.
But he said; I have a request.
He told the Angel of death; I have one request.
And that is, that you take me as close as you can, to Jerusalem;
take me as close as you can, distance of throwing a stone, and let me die over there.
If I'm not able to enter into Jerusalem alive, at least take me as close as possible to Jerusalem so that, I can die next to it.
I can die next to the walls of Jerusalem.
So Musaعليه السلام was living with the hope that one day, he will enter into the Holy Land.
And the only reason; why he didn't, is because of who?
Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
They were on the Gates of Jerusalem, they were on the gates.
Musa(موسى) told them; Let's go and fight.
They said;
فَاذْهَبْ أَنتَ وَرَبُّكَ فَقَاتِلَا إِنَّا هَاهُنَا قَاعِدُونَ۝
Go and fight with your Lord, we're gonna stay right here.
Then two men;
أَنْعَمَ ٱللَّهُ عَلَيْهِمَا
Two men; who fear Allahسُبحانه وتعالى whom, Allah has bestowed his blessing;
they came to Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) and they told them;
اُدْخُلُوا عَلَيْهِمُ الْبَابَ فَإِذَا دَخَلْتُمُوهُ فَإِنَّكُمْ غَالِبُونَ ۚ
Just walk through the gates and if you do so, you will win, and they refused.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى did not give Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل), the honour of entering into Jerusalem because they don't deserve it; they're not ready yet.
And because of that, Musa(موسى) was not able to enter into Jerusalem neither was his brother Haroon(هارون).
And Musaعليه السلام died in Al-Tih(تیح); died in the wilderness.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
فلمَّا جاءَهُ صَكَّهُ ففقأَ فرجعَ إلى ربِّهِ فقالَ أرسَلتني إلى عبدٍ لا يريدُ الموتَ
فردَّ اللَّهُ إليْهِ عينَهُ قالَ ارجِع فقل لَهُ يضعُ يدَهُ على متنِ ثورٍ
فلَهُ بِكلِّ ما غطَّت يدُهُ بِكلِّ شعرةٍ سنةٌ
قالَ أي ربِّ ثمَّ مَه قالَ الموتُ
قالَ فالآنَ فسألَ اللَّهَ أن يدنيَهُ منَ الأرضِ المقدَّسةِ رميةً بحجرٍ
قالَ رسولُ اللَّهِ صلَّى اللَّهُ عليْهِ وسلَّمَ فلو كنتُ ثَمَّ لأريتُكم قبرَهُ إلى جانبِ الطَّريقِ تحتَ الْكثيبِ الأحمرِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ has seen the grave of Musa(موسى)
and Rasool Ullah says, in the Hadith(حديث) of Al-Isra(اَلْاِسْرى);
مررتُ بموسَى فاذا هو قائمٌ يُصلِّي في قبرِه
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that; Indeed, in Al-Isra(اَلْاِسْرى), when Rasool Allah ﷺ travelled to Jerusalem;
he passed next to the grave of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى), and he saw him praying in his grave to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
We'll move on to a story; an interesting story; an amazing story, that occurred with Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى).
And the reason why I delayed it until now, is because we don't know exactly where the story fits, in terms of the chronological order of events.
And this is the story of Musa(موسى) and Al-Khadr(الخضر).
It is a story of Ajaa'ib(عجائب) of astonishing events from the beginning till the end.
And the way this event happened, is that, Musa(موسى) stood one day on the minbar(منبر); on the pulpit, and was speaking to Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
So, one of the men of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); the children of Israel(اسرائيل) stood up and said;
Oh Musa(موسى)! Who is the most knowledgeable man, who's the most knowledgeable person?
So Musa(موسى) said; I am.
Because, he was the Prophet of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; he was the Nabi(نَبِي); he is the one who's receiving revelation from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
According to his knowledge, he is the most knowledgeable person.
Because he is the Nabi(نَبِي); he is the Prophet; he is the one who has a direct link between him and Allah; receiving the Wahi(وحى) from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So he said; I am.
And this Hadith(حديث) again in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى); How come you did not say; Allah-u-Aalam(اللَّهُ أَعْلمَ)?
How come you did not say that, Allah knows best, who's the most knowledgeable person?
There is a man, who has knowledge that you do not have.
Musa(موسى) did not say that, I am the most knowledgeable because he is proud or because he's arrogant.
That's not the reason; Musa(موسى) is a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; he would not do that.
But he said that, he is the most knowledgeable person because that is according to his knowledge.
So when it came to the knowledge of Musa(موسى) that, he is not the most knowledgeable person.
He was so humble that he requested from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to allow him to be a student of that man.
He said; Oh Allah! How can I learn from him?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him; You can meet him in the place, where you miss or you lose your fish.
That is where, you will meet this learned man. this wise man, and the name of this man is Al-Khadr(الخضر).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says in a Hadith(حديث); an authentic Hadith(حديث) that the reason, why he was called the Al-Khadr(الخضر)?
Because Al-Khadr(الخضر); an Arabic means; green.
The reason, why he was named Al-Khadr(الخضر)?
Is because he was one sitting on dry grass, and when he stood up; the grass under him was green.
So that is why, he was given the name Al-Khadr(الخضر);
A karamah(الكرامۃ); some Karamat(کرامات) were happening on the hands of Al-Khadr(الخضر).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى) that you would meet Al-Khadr(الخضر) in this specific place.
So Musa(موسى) took with him his servant, and who was the servant of  Musa(موسى)?
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون).
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون), and we're gonna talk about Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) later.
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) was the servant of Musa(موسى).
And because he was close to Musa(موسى) and learning from Musa(موسى)
then, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى appointed him to be the Nabi(نَبِي) of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) when Musa(موسى) passed away.
Because he was close to Musa(موسى) and he was learning from Musa(موسى).
That's how we learn by being close to the learned ones.
So this servant of Musa(موسى) learn the wisdom and the knowledge from Musa(موسى),
and then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى appointed him to be the Nabi(نَبِي) after Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون) passed away.
So Musa(موسى) went with his servant and it's mentioned in Qur'an;
وَإِذْ قَالَ لِفَتَاهُ
He and his servant; they started embarking on this amazing and wonderful trip.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَإِذْ قَالَ مُوسَىٰ لِفَتَاهُ لَا أَبْرَحُ حَتَّىٰ أَبْلُغَ مَجْمَعَ الْبَحْرَيْنِ أَوْ أَمْضِيَ حُقُبًا۝
And remember when Musa(موسى) said to his boy servant;
I will not give up travelling until I reach the junction of the two seas, or until I spend years and years in traveling.
So, the place you will meet him is the junction between the two seas.
Some of the scholars say that, these two seas are the Red Sea and the Mediterranean Sea.
So you'll meet him in the junction between these two seas; Allah-u-Aalam(اللَّهُ أَعْلمَ).
Musa(موسى) was so determined to go and learn.
He said; I would reach to the junction of the seas even if it would take me years in travelling.
Allahu Akbar(الله اكبر)! Musa(موسى) has so much knowledge already.
He's already receiving the Wahi(وحى) from Allah.
But because he knew that there is a man has some other knowledge that he does not have.
He's willing to make all of this travelling to go and learn.
This is how Talib-al'ilm(طالب العلم) should be!
The students of knowledge needs to sacrifice.
You need to sacrifice to learn.
Musa(موسى); even though, he was knowledgeable.
He did not say, what I have is enough, he travelled all the way, and he said, I would even travel years, if I need to do so, to go and learn.
So we need to sacrifice if we want to learn.
We need to sacrifice time and effort and money to learn.
The servant of Musa(موسى) was carrying this fish.
It was a dead fish.
They camped in a certain area and they went to sleep.
But something amazing happened, and this is the starting of the amazing things in this trip.
This fish woke up and marched all the way to the sea, and started swimming in the sea in front of the eyes of Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون).
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) saw this dead fish wake up, and then march all the way to the sea,
and then start swimming in the sea, and it's making a tunnel behind it.
السربة
He forgot to tell us about it, and they went to bed and then they travel.
They travelled the next day.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَلَمَّا بَلَغَا مَجْمَعَ بَيْنِهِمَا
Then they reach to the junction of the two seas.
Musa(موسى) now was tired and hungry.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says; Musa(موسى) did not become tired and hungry until that moment;
All throughout this trip until that moment, Musa(موسى) never felt exhausted and then Musa(موسى) said;
فَلَمَّا جَاوَزَا قَالَ لِفَتَىٰهُ ءَاتِنَا غَدَآءَنَا لَقَدْ لَقِينَا مِن سَفَرِنَا هَٰذَا نَصَبًا۝
So, they reached to the junction of the two seas; they slept there and then, they travelled the next day.
So when they had passed further on, beyond the fixed place,
Musa(موسى) said to his boy servant; Bring us our morning meal, truly we have suffered much fatigue in this journey.
Only then, did Musa(موسى) feel fatigue, and he told his servants bring us the fish.
Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) remembered; what happened to the fish.
He said;
قَالَ أَرَأَيْتَ إِذْ أَوَيْنَا إِلَى الصَّخْرَةِ فَإِنِّي نَسِيتُ الْحُوتَ وَمَا أَنسَانِيهُ إِلَّا الشَّيْطَانُ أَنْ أَذْكُرَهُ ۚ
He said; Do you remember when we betook ourselves to the rock; that's where they slept; next to the rock.
I indeed forgot the fish, none but Shaytan(شَيْطَانْ) made me forget to remember it.
It took its course into the sea in a strange way.
Musa(موسى) said; That is what we were looking for.
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى) you will find Al-Khadr(الخضر) in the place where you lose the fish.
So Musa(موسى) said;
ذَٰلِكَ مَا كُنَّا نَبْغِ ۚ
That's what I was waiting for.
قَالَ ذَٰلِكَ مَا كُنَّا نَبْغِ ۚ فَٱرْتَدَّا عَلَىٰٓ ءَاثَارِهِمَا قَصَصًا۝
Musa(موسى) said; That is what we have been seeking.
So they went back retracing their footsteps.
Now, Musa(موسى) and Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون); they have to travel back the same way.
Because, Allah told Musa(موسى) you would find him in the place where you lose the fish.
Already, they've travelled a long distance. Now, they have to retract back.
So, Musa(موسى) and Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون) are retracing their steps back.
On their way back; they passed by a man who was covered under his blanket.
So Musa(موسى) saw that man, and he told them; Assalam-o-Alaykum(اسلام عليكم)!
So the man stood up and said;
أَنَّى بأرضِكَ السَّلامُ
He said; People over here do not know about Salam(سلام).
Who are you?
Musa(موسى) said; I am Musa(موسى)!
So the man said; Musa(موسى); Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
Are you the Musa(موسى) of the children of Israel(اسرائيل)?
Musa(موسى) said; Yes!
Al-Khadr(الخضر) already knew him and heard about him.
So when he said; I am Musa(موسى), he said; Are you the Musa(موسى) of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل)?
He wants to make sure. He said; Yes!
I'm Musa(موسى); Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
He said; I am Al-Khadr(الخضر)!
Musaعليه السلام told Al-Khadr(الخضر);
I want to learn from you; humble; a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allah; he's telling this man, who might not be a Nabi(نَبِي).
Because, there's a difference of opinion whether, Al-Khadr(الخضر) is a Nabi(نَبِي) or not.
Some scholars say; he is, some say; he's not.
And it is an undetermined issue because, there is no evidence that he was a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allah.
He could have been of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) or he could have been a Wali(ولي) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So, we don't know.
Regardless, it shows that Musa(موسى) wanted to learn from him, and he came in a very humble manner, and he said; I want to study; under you.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) said; I have knowledge, that Allah has taught me, that you do not have;
and you have knowledge, which Allah taught you that, I do not have.
So, Al-Khadr(الخضر); he knew, that he has some knowledge that is unknown to Musa(موسى),
and Musa(موسى) has some knowledge, that is unknown to him.
Musa(موسى) said; I want to follow you.
أَتَّبِعُكَ
I want to follow you.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) said; You will not be able to follow me because you will have no patience.
وَكَيْفَ تَصْبِرُ عَلَىٰ مَا لَمْ تُحِطْ بِهِۦ خُبْرًا۝
How will you have patience on something that you did not know?
You gonna see things that are amazing and astonishing and you're not gonna have patience.
Musa(موسى) said; Let me follow you! Let me follow you!
Al-Khadr(الخضر) did not want to reject this student of knowledge, but he set a condition,
he said;
قَالَ فَإِنِ اتَّبَعْتَنِي فَلَا تَسْأَلْنِي عَن شَيْءٍ حَتَّىٰ أُحْدِثَ لَكَ مِنْهُ ذِكْرًا۝
He said; If you follow me, asked me not about anything, till I myself mentioned it to you.
This is the condition, you follow me; but you do not question my actions.
You accept what you see; don't argue.
Musa(موسى) said; I agree.
So this was their agreement.
They began this trip.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) is taking Musa(موسى) to Wonderland.
It started with Al-Khadr(الخضر) and Musa(موسى) crossing the sea.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) wanted to travel to the other side of the sea.
So he was looking for transportation; for a ship.
So he found the ship and he asked them to deliver them to the other side.
It turned out that the sailors; the owners of the ship; knew Al-Khadr(الخضر), and they offered him a free ride.
We're gonna carry you for free.
They didn't do it; because they know Musa(موسى); they did it; because they know Al-Khadr(الخضر).
So, this was a favour done to who? To Al-Khadr(الخضر); specifically.
They knew Al-Khadr(الخضر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ mentions that in the Hadith(حديث);
فحملوهما بغير نَوْلٍ
They carried them without any compensation; why?
Because they knew Al-Khadr(الخضر).
The first thing that happened when they were on this ship; Musa(موسى) and Al-Khadr(الخضر) was sitting together on the deck;
and a bird landed on the deck; and then that bird dipped its beak in the ocean; in the sea to drink.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) told Musa(موسى); Did you see that bird?
Musa(موسى) said; Yes!
Al-Khadr(الخضر) said; My knowledge plus your knowledge compared to the knowledge of Allah is like; what that bird has taken from the sea.
That's one drop, that the bird has taken from the sea is like; my knowledge plus your knowledge.
You said that, you're the most knowledgeable person on the face of the Earth.
Allah told you that, there's somebody who has more knowledge than you;
we together; me and you together combined the knowledge of the most two knowledgeable people on the Earth,
compared to the knowledge of Allah is less than what, that bird has taken from the sea.
That is the knowledge of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; the ocean of the knowledge of Allah.
That's the first lesson Al-Khadr(الخضر) is giving to Musa(موسى).
Our knowledge is nothing compared to the knowledge of Allah.
And then Al-Khadr(الخضر); When the sailors were busy with work,
Al-Khadr(الخضر) took an axe, and he broke a slab on the ship, and he plucked out a panel.
He destroyed part of the ship.
He took his axe and he started destroying it when the sailors were busy; they didn't know what was happening.
And then he pulled out the panel from the ship.
Musa(موسى); when he saw this, he couldn't believe his eyes.
Because these men are doing you a favour;
they're doing it for you not for me; they're doing you a favour by giving you a ride for free
and you destroyed their ship.
Musaعليه السلام said;
فَٱنطَلَقَا حَتَّىٰٓ إِذَا رَكِبَا فِى ٱلسَّفِينَةِ خَرَقَهَا ۖ قَالَ أَخَرَقْتَهَا لِتُغْرِقَ أَهْلَهَا لَقَدْ جِئْتَ شَيْـًٔا إِمْرًا۝
So they then proceeded till when they embark the ship; Al-Khadr(الخضر) scuttled it.
Musa(موسى) said; Have you scuttled it in order to drown his people;
verily, you have committed that thing that is evil.
How could you do this?
How could you do this for the people who are doing you a favour?
Is this; is this how you pay them back?
They give you a ride for free and you destroy their ship.
Do you want them to drown in the sea?
Al-Khadr(الخضر) said; Didn't I tell you, you're not gonna have patience?
The agreement was that, you don't question my actions.
قَالَ أَلَمْ أَقُل لَّكَ إِنَّكَ لَن تَسْتَطِيعَ مَعِيَ صَبْرًا۝
Didn't I tell you, you're not gonna have patience.
Musa(موسى) did not intentionally break his promise; Musa(موسى) forgot.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
وَكانَتِ الأُولَى مِن مُوسَى نِسْيانًا
The first time, Musa(موسى) forgot.
Musa(موسى) forgot; forgot his promise.
So he told Al-Khadr(الخضر);
قَالَ لَا تُؤَاخِذْنِى بِمَا نَسِيتُ وَلَا تُرْهِقْنِى مِنْ أَمْرِى عُسْرًا۝
Musa(موسى) said; Call me not to account for what I forgot, and be not hard upon me for my affair with you.
Musa(موسى) said; Forgive me for this mistake, and don't be hard,
meaning; I mean, even though our agreement is; if I question you, our agreement is breached.
But he said; I mean, give me another chance.
Don't be strict; give me another chance.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) said; I'll give you another chance.
Even though, the agreement is over with, Al-Khadr(الخضر) could have told Musa(موسى), you have to leave.
But Al-Khadr(الخضر) said; I will give you another chance.
They reached to the shore on the other side.
And they passed by children who were playing.
What seemed to be innocent children playing?
Al-Khadr(الخضر) walked up to one of these children.
He picked him up; he grabbed his head; and he tore it off.
He tore off the head of the child; he killed him.
Musaعليه السلام remembers exactly his promise.
Now, he remembers it.
But we know the nature of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى); he can never approve evil.
If he sees something that is wrong; he speaks out against it.
So Musaعليه السلام; even though, he knows that he has given a promise not to question;
when he saw this crime in front of his eyes, he said;
فَانطَلَقَا حَتَّىٰ إِذَا لَقِيَا غُلَامًا فَقَتَلَهُ قَالَ أَقَتَلْتَ نَفْسًا زَكِيَّةً بِغَيْرِ نَفْسٍ لَّقَدْ جِئْتَ شَيْئًا نُّكْرًا۝
Have you killed an innocent person who killed none?
Verily, you have committed that dreadful thing.
How could you do this?
This child is innocent.
He didn't do anything.
How come you killed them?
Al-Khadr(الخضر) said;
قَالَ أَلَمْ أَقُل لَّكَ إِنَّكَ لَن تَسْتَطِيعَ مَعِيَ صَبْرًا۝
Didn't I tell you, you're not gonna have patience.
So the anger of Musa(موسى) subceeded, and he told Al-Khadr(الخضر); This is my last chance.
قَالَ إِن سَأَلْتُكَ عَن شَىْءٍ بَعْدَهَا فَلَا تُصَٰحِبْنِى ۖ
He said; Give me one more chance.
Three strikes or you're out; this is my last chance.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قَالَ إِن سَأَلْتُكَ عَن شَىْءٍ بَعْدَهَا فَلَا تُصَٰحِبْنِى ۖ قَدْ بَلَغْتَ مِن لَّدُنِّى عُذْرًا۝
Musa(موسى) said; If I asked you anything after this, keep me not in your company, you have received the excuse from me.
That's it.
You have done your part.
And you have forgive me enough.
One more time; give me one more chance; the third chance.
If I break the promise for a third time, then you can go your own way.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) agreed.
فَانطَلَقَا حَتَّىٰ إِذَا أَتَيَا أَهْلَ قَرْيَةٍ اسْتَطْعَمَا أَهْلَهَا فَأَبَوْا أَن يُضَيِّفُوهُمَا
Musa(موسى) and Al-Khadr(الخضر) walked into a town, and they asked the people of that town to feed them.
It was in their law; in their religion, and in our religion too, and that the guest has a right upon you.
You are not doing the guests the favour by providing for the guests for three days.
And it's an obligation on you to help the guest and take care of that guests for three days.
After three days, you can hold back if you want, or you can continue, but its upto you.
But for the first three days, it's an obligation on the Muslim community to take care of the guest.
So, Musa(موسى) and Al-Khadr(الخضر); they walked into that town; they asked them to feed them; they provided them with nothing.
They were very stingy people; they refuse to help; they did not extend any helping hand to them.
While, Al-Khadr(الخضر) and Musa(موسى) were walking down the street in that town.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) saw a wall that was about to fall down; cracked wall; very weak; it was about to tumble and fall down.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) started erecting the wall again.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) stopped, and he was rebuilding that wall without taking permission from anyone;
without being requested to do so by anyone; and he's doing it for free; he's building that wall for free.
Musa(موسى) saw contradiction in this.
The people of the ship; the sailors of the ship who are doing you a favour for free.
You destroyed their ship.
The child who's innocent; you kill him.
And these people who refuse to help us; you're doing them a favour for free.
The people who will help you; you do what seems to be harming them.
And the people who are not doing you any good; you are helping them.
So, Musa(موسى) had the suggestion to offer. He said;
قَالَ لَوْ شِئْتَ لَتَّخَذْتَ عَلَيْهِ أَجْرًا۝
Why don't you charge them for building the wall?
Why don't you charge them?
Al-Khadr(الخضر) said;
قَالَ هَٰذَا فِرَاقُ بَيْنِى وَبَيْنِكَ ۚ
This is the end of our agreement.
You have breached the agreement; you have to go your way, and I go my way.
It's done.
But Al-Khadr(الخضر) said; Before you leave;
سَأُنَبِّئُكَ بِتَأْوِيلِ مَا لَمْ تَسْتَطِع عَّلَيْهِ صَبْرًا۝
I will tell you the interpretation of the things, you did not have patience on.
I will interpret for you what was happening.
أَمَّا ٱلسَّفِينَةُ فَكَانَتْ لِمَسَٰكِينَ يَعْمَلُونَ فِى ٱلْبَحْرِ فَأَرَدتُّ أَنْ أَعِيبَهَا وَكَانَ وَرَآءَهُم مَّلِكٌ يَأْخُذذُ كُلَّ سَفِينَةٍ غَصْبًا۝
He said; I'll tell you first about the ship.
That ship belong to some poor sailors.
That was their source of living.
They would use that ship for transportation or for fishing.
But that was their only source of income.
And there was a king on the way, who was attacking the area.
And that King is going to take every ship that seems to be in a good condition.
So the king is gonna come in that area, and is gonna take by force, and confiscate every ship that seemed to be in a good condition.
So, Al-Khadr(الخضر) wanted to break this ship.
So that, it seems to be an old destroyed ship.
So the king would leave it alone.
And therefore, these poor sailors would not have lost their ship and then they can fix it after the king leaves.
That is why, I broke off a panel from it.
So at least the sailors will have their ship, even though, it's not functioning; they will have it.
But if I did not do this, the king would take the whole thing away.
And they would lose their source of income.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى brought for these poor sailors a blessing through the hands of Al-Khadr(الخضر).
And by the way, this Ayah(آية) has been used as a supporting evidence for the issue of; Al-Fiqh al-masa'il al-mafasid(الفقه المسائل المفاسد).
And the scholars derived the rule from this Ayah(آية) that,
if you are confronted with two evils, and you must choose between one of them; you choose the least,
or like they say; necessary evil.
If you have to choose between two evils; choose the least.
There were two evils here;
One evil was; the king takes away the ship.
The other evil is; I break a panel, which is the least evil; breaking a panel, breaking that slab.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) had this Fiqh(فقه) of choosing the least of the two evils.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
As for the ship; it belonged to poor people working in the sea.
So, I wish to make a defective damage in it, as there was a king behind them who seized every ship by force.
Next the story of Al-Ghulam(الغلام);
وَأَمَّا ٱلْغُلَٰمُ فَكَانَ أَبَوَاهُ مُؤْمِنَيْنِ فَخَشِينَآ أَن يُرْهِقَهُمَا طُغْيَٰنًا وَكُفْرًا۝
He said; That young boy; he was going to grow up to be a Kafir(كافر); a disbeliever, and a tyrant.
يُرْهِقَهُمَا طُغْيَٰنًا وَكُفْرًا۝
Tughyan(طُغْيَٰن) is tyranny and Kuffr(كفر) is disbelief.
So, this young boy will grow up not only to be a nonbeliever in Allah, but he will grow up to be a tyrant, and will cause his parents; hardship and difficulty.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wanted the best for this family.
So Allah wanted to take away the life of that young boy,
and to replace the family with another child that will be nice and kind to his parents, and will be a believer in Allah.
And this shows you that you never know, what lies on the other side.
These parents; let's think about their reaction when their child was killed; What do you think their reaction was?
They would cry, and they would mourn, and they would be upset and sorry.
Because they do not know what Allah is planning for them.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) knew the plan, but they didn't.
They were losing a child, but they did not know that, that was the best for them.
Because if this child grew up and was living, he would cause them; hardship and difficulty.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wanted to take away this child and to give them another child, that will grow up and become kind to them.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى was hiding for this family good in what appeared to be evil.
You might love something, but it's not good for you.
And you might dislike something, but it's good for you.
Allah says; As for the boy, his parents were believers, and we feared lest he should oppress them by rebellion and disbelief.
So we intended that their Lord should change him for them, for one better in righteousness and near to mercy.
Next the story of the wall.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) erected the wall.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) said; That wall belonged to two orphans in the town.
Beneath the wall was a treasure.
Al-Khadr(الخضر) was instructed to build the wall.
So the orphans would grow up and retrieve their treasure later.
Because if the wall falls down; Al-Khadr(الخضر) left the wall alone, what would happen?
It would fall down, and the treasure will be exposed.
And these orphans are young, and they will not be able to defend their treasure.
I mean, we know that the people of that town are not gonna leave that treasure alone.
Those people who refuse to feed Al-Khadr(الخضر) and Musa(موسى); who refused to even give them some food;
they're not gonna leave this treasure with two kids; they're gonna take it away from them.
If these people were so miserable and stingy that they didn't even feed Musa(موسى) and Al-Khadr(الخضر);
we wouldn't expect them to be honest with the two orphans.
They're gonna steal that money; they're going to rip them off.
Therefore Allah wanted Al-Khadr(الخضر) to build the wall again.
So that, the orphans would grow up and when they're old and strong; they would be able to retrieve their treasure.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَأَمَّا الْجِدَارُ فَكَانَ لِغُلَامَيْنِ يَتِيمَيْنِ فِي الْمَدِينَةِ وَكَانَ تَحْتَهُ كَنزٌ لَّهُمَا وَكَانَ أَبُوهُمَا صَالِحًا
And as for the wall; it belong to two orphan boys in the town; and there was under it a treasure belonging to them;
and their father was a righteous man.
Underline this.
Why did Allah send the Al-Khadr(الخضر) to rebuild the wall?
Why?
Because the father of the two orphans was what?
Righteous.
Allah protected the orphans; Allah protected the children because the father was righteous.
If you want Allah to protect your children; then protect them with your good deeds.
Protect them with Al-Amal as-Salih(اَلْعَمَل اَلصَّالِحْ).
Saeed ibn Musaiyyib(سعيد ابن مصيّب); Al-Taba'i Al-Kabir(التابعى الكبير); one of the major Taba'een(تابعين); he told his son;
يابنئى انى لاستكثر من الاعمال الصالحة حتى يحفظك الله
He said; Oh my son! I am doing so many good deeds, because I want the Allah to protect you with them.
Our good deeds are protection for our children.
If we want Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to take care of our children; let's take care of them by our good deeds.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will take care of them even if, you are not around.
This man was dead; and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى took care of his orphans;
Allah send Al-Khadr(الخضر) specifically,
specifically send Al-Khadr(ال خضر) to go and fulfill that mission,
why?
To serve that man who died, because he was righteous.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will take care of your affairs; don't worry!
Allah will take care of you; whether you're dead or alive; if you take care of the orders of Allah.
احفظ الله يحفظك
Take care of the commandments of Allah; what will happen?
Allah will take care of you.
وَكَانَ أَبُوهُمَا صَالِحًا فَأَرَادَ رَبُّكَ أَن يَبْلُغَا أَشُدَّهُمَا وَيَسْتَخْرِجَا كَنزَهُمَا رَحْمَةً مِّن رَّبِّكَ ۚ
Their father was a righteous man and your Lord intended that they should attain their age of full strength,
and take out their treasure as a mercy from your Lord.
And then Al-Khadr(الخضر) is saying something important;
وَمَا فَعَلْتُهُ عَنْ أَمْرِي ۚ
And I did them not of my own accord.
These things that you saw me do; Allah was one who's telling me to do them.
This is knowledge from Allah.
And that is how the believer should be.
You never give credit to yourself, you give credit to whom the credit belongs to, and that is Allah.
This is the story of Musa(موسى) and Al-Khadr(الخضر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
يَرْحَمُ اللَّهُ مُوسَى ، لَوَكَانَ صَبَرَ يُقَصَّ عَلَيْنَا مِنْ أَمْرِهِمَا
May Allah have mercy on Musa(موسى)! If he was patient; then we would have been told more about this amazing story.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wants to know more about the details of the life of this learned, wise man; Al-Khadr(الخضر).
We finish the story of Syedina Musaعليه السلام and we like to end his story by mentioning a few of his Fadha'il(فضائل); Manaqib(مناقب).
These are not all of them; we'll just mention a few.
Musaعليه السلام was the most frequently mentioned Nabi(نَبِي) in Qur'an.
He was mentioned more than any other Nabi(نَبِي).
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has praised Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) and said;
وَكَانَ عِندَ اللَّهِ وَجِيهًا۝
He was distinguished; he was noble; he was honoured.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is the one who gave him that title.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَاذْكُرْ فِي الْكِتَابِ مُوسَىٰ ۚ إِنَّهُ كَانَ مُخْلَصًا وَكَانَ رَسُولًا نَّبِيًّا۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; And mentioned in the book; Musa(موسى)! Verily he was chosen, and he was a messenger, and the prophet.
He was chosen.
مُخْلَصًا
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى chose him from out of mankind.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
لا تفضلوني على موسى فإن الناس يصعقون يوم القيامة، فأكون أول من يفيق،
واجدو موسی باتشا بقائمۃ العرش فلا ادری فصعق فافاق قبلی ام جوزی بصعق الطور رواہ البخاری و مسلم
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; Don't prefer me over Musa(موسى).
And we talked about what Rasool Allah ﷺ means by this.
It is our belief and we know that, Muhammadﷺ is the best of mankind.
But we know what Muhammadﷺ means of this; is his humbleness; صلی اللہ علیہ وسلم.
Don't prefer me over Musa(موسى);
Rasool Ullah does not want us to go to the non-believers and start saying;
We have Muhammadﷺ you have Musa(موسى); Muhammadﷺ is better than Musa(موسى); No!
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ does not want us to fight with the non-believers, and end up taking a stance against the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Because Musa(موسى) is a Muslim and Eesa(عيسى) is a Muslim.
Therefore, Rasool Allah ﷺ does not want us to get into that.
He said;
لا تفضلونا على موسى
Don't say that, I am better than Musa(موسى).
Because, Rasool Allah ﷺ says; On the Day of Judgment everybody will go through As-Sa'aq(صائق), that is the shock.
Everyone will go through that shock, and everyone will be unconscious and dead.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
And I will be the first one to rise up, but I will find out that Musa(موسى) is already grabbing the throne of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And I don't know whether, he was excluded from the shock
or whether, he did not go through the shock because, he has already went through it when he asked to see Allah.
You remember, when we talked about Musa(موسى) asking to see Allah;
وَخَرَّصَعِقًا
He went through a shock and he fell unconscious.
So Muhammadﷺ said; Maybe Allah did not put him through the shock on the day of judgment
because he has already been through a Shock in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا); that's enough.
Once is enough.
So, Musaعليه السلام will be excluded from that shock on the Day of Judgment.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ once was distributing Al-Ghanaam(الغنام); the spoils of war; he was giving out.
So one man came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
إن هذهِ لقسمةٌ ما يُرادُ بها وجهُ اللهِ
He said; The way you're dividing this wealth, you're not doing it for the sake of Allah.
A man comes to Rasool Allah ﷺ and tells him; You are not doing it, for the sake of Allah.
Imagine this! You're speaking to the Messenger of Allah, whom Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to chose, and you accuse him of being unfair and unjust.
Obviously, Rasool Ullah was upset.
And the Sahabah(صحابه) said; We could see anger on his face.
But then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
رَحِمَ اللَّهُ مُوسَى قدْ أُوذِيَ بأَكْثَرَ مِن هذا فَصَبَرَ
May Allah have mercy on Musa(موسى)! He was harmed more than this, and he was patient.
Musa(موسى) went through a lot.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says, about Musa(موسى);
يَا قَوْمِ لِمَ تُؤْذُونَنِي وَقَد تَّعْلَمُونَ أَنِّي رَسُولُ اللَّهِ إِلَيْكُمْ ۖ
Oh my people! Why do you harm me, when you know that I'm the Messenger of Allah to you.
So he went through a lot of harm.
Nevertheless, he was patient, and Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
May Allah have mercy on him! He went through more than this, and he was patient.
Another one of the Fadha'il(فضائل) of Musaعليه السلام;
Rasool Allah ﷺ mentioned one fadhilah(فضيله) for Musa(موسى) in Al-Asra(الاسراء) and one in Al-Mairaj(المعراج).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ went to Al-Asra(الاسراء); Al-Asra(الاسراء) is a trip from Makkah(مكه) to Jerusalem,
and Mairaj(معراج) is from Jerusalem to meet with Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was going in Al-Asra(الاسراء) from Makkah(مكه) to Jerusalem; Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
I passed next to the grave of Musa(موسى), and I saw him praying in his grave.
And then, when Rasool Allah ﷺ went in Al-Mairaj(المعراج);
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; I met with Musa(موسى) in; As-Sama as-Sadisah(السماء السادسة); in the sixth heaven.
Nobody was higher than Musa(موسى) except, Sayidina Ibrahimعليه السلام, in the seventh heaven.
Musa(موسى) was the highest in the sixth heaven.
That is one of the Faza'il(فضائل) of Syedina Musaعليه السلام.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
عُرِضَتْ عليَّ الأُممُ ، فرأيتُ النبيَّ ومَعهُ الرَّهْطُ ، والنبيَّ ومعهُ الرجُلَ والرَّجُلانِ ، والنبيَّ وليسَ مَعهُ أحَدٌ ،
The umam(امم); the nations of the world were presented to me.
I saw some prophets, they had a small group.
Some of the prophets had a man or two, following them on the Day of Judgment.
Imagine a Nabi(نَبِي) comes with one or two men with him, that's it.
All of his life; he was making Da'wah(دعوة), and the result was one or two men, that's it.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
And I saw some of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) and no one was with them.
There were some Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء); they have no followers whatsoever.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
ثم عرض لِي سَوادٌ عظيمٌ ،
And then I saw a huge nation.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; I desired; I wished that this would be my ummah(امة).
أُمَّتي هذِه
Rasool Ullah asked the two angels who are with him, Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) and Mikail(ميكائيل).
This is a dream, which Rasool Allah ﷺ was seeing.
Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل) came and took his right hand; Mikail(ميكائل) his left hand and they took him in this trip.
So, Rasool Ullah said; Is this my ummah(امة)?
Rasool Ullah wanted this to be his ummah(امة); because this was huge.
They said; No!
هذِه اُمَّتِ مُوسى
These are Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
These are the ummah(امة) of Musa(موسى); Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
But look to the right side!
فَإِذَا بِسَوَادٌ عَظِيم يَمْلَأُ الأُفُقَ
I look to the right side, and I saw a nation that is filling the horizon.
And then, they told me; Look to the other side!
So, I looked in the other side, and I saw a nation that is filling the horizon.
They said this is your ummah(امة),
and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will include with them 70,000 of your ummah(امة) will enter into Jannah(جنة) without going through Hisaab(حساب);
without going through the regular accounting of everyone else.
70,000 of this ummah(امة) will enter into paradise without going through the accountability stage that everyone else has to go through.
This is a Karamah(كرامه) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to this ummah(امة).
But we also learned from the Hadith(حديث) that, the second largest nation is the nation of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل); the children of Israel(اسرائيل).
Another Hadith(حديث) narrated by Al-Imam Ahmad(الاِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ);
Rasool Allah ﷺ when he went to Hajj(حَجْ); he passed through a valley,
he asked; what is the name of this valley?
قالو هذا وادي الازرق
The name of this valley is the Azraq(ازرق) valley.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
كأني أنظر إلى موسى وهو هابطاً من الثنية، وله جؤار إلى الله عزوجل بالتلبية
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; As if I can see Musa(موسى) coming down from this hill, making Hajj(حَجْ) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, and making Talbiyah(تلبيه).
So, Musaعليه السلام made Hajj(حَجْ); He made Hajj(حَجْ) to the house of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Yunus Ibn matta(يونس ابن مطّه) made Hajj(حَجْ),
and another Ahadith(احاديث); we have narrations of other Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) making Hajj(حَجْ) like, Hud(هود) and Saleh(صالح).
So the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; they made Hajj(حَجْ) to the house of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى,
and Allah was making Muhammadﷺ see them, as if it was in front of his eyes.
He saw Musa(موسى), when he was coming down that hill,
and he saw Yunus ibn Matta(يونس ابن مطّه) coming down that hill, wearing wool clothes, over a red camel.
These are some of the Fadha'il(فضائل) of Musaعليه السلام.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تسلیما کثیرا